I've actually been waiting by the phone
لقد كنت أنتظر على الهاتف
for a call from TED for years.
لمكالمة من تيد لسنوات.
And in fact, in 2000, I was ready to talk about eBay, but no call.
وفي الواقع، عام 2000، كنت مستعداً للحديث عن eBay ..لكن لم يتصلوا.
In 2003, I was ready to do a talk
في عام 2003 كنت مستعداً للحديث
about the Skoll Foundation and social entrepreneurship. No call.
عن مؤسسة سكول والأعمال الإجتماعية. لم يتصلوا.
In 2004, I started Participant Productions
عام 2004 بدأت مشاركة الإنتاج
and we had a really good first year, and no call.
وقد مررنا بالفعل بسنتنا الأولى الناجحة، ولم يتصلوا.
And finally, I get a call last year,
وأخيراً أستقبلت مكالمة في العام الماضي،
and then I have to go up after J.J. Abrams.
ثم ينبغي علي صعود المسرح بعد J.J. Abrams.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
You've got a cruel sense of humor, TED.
لديكم حس قبيح بالمرح، منظمي تيد.
When I first moved to Hollywood from Silicon Valley,
عندما أنتقلت من وادي السيليكون إلى هوليوود،
I had some misgivings.
إنتباتني بعض الهواجس.
But I found that there were some advantages to being in Hollywood.
لكني وجدت أن هناك بعض المزايا لوجودك في هوليوود.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And, in fact, some advantages to owning your own media company.
وفي الواقع، بعض المزايا من إمتلاكك لشركة إعلامية.
And I also found that Hollywood and Silicon Valley
وكذلك وجدت أن هوليوود ووادي السيليكون
have a lot more in common than I would have dreamed.
لديهما الكثير المشترك عما كنت أحلم به.
Hollywood has its sex symbols, and the Valley has its sex symbols.
لدى هوليوود رموزها الجنسية، ولدى الوادي رموزه الجنسية.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Hollywood has its rivalries, and the Valley has its rivalries.
لهوليوود منافسات داخلية ، وللوادي منافسات داخلية.
Hollywood gathers around power tables,
تتجمع هوليوود حول طاولات السلطة،
and the Valley gathers around power tables.
ويجتمع الوادي حول طاولات السلطة.
So it turned out there was a lot more in common
لذا فقد أتضح أن لديهما الكثير مشترك،
than I would have dreamed.
مما كنت أحلم به.
But I'm actually here today to tell a story.
لكني هنا اليوم لأحكي قصة.
And part of it is a personal story. When Chris invited me to speak,
وجزء من قصتي الشخصية. عندما دعاني كريس للحديث،
he said, people think of you as a bit of an enigma,
قال أن الناس يفكرون بك ك-- كشخص غامض،
and they want to know what drives you a bit.
ويرغبون في معرفة ما يحركك قليلاً.
And what really drives me is a vision of the future
والذي يحركني حقاً هو -- هو رؤية للمستقبل
that I think we all share.
التي أعتقد أننا جميعاً نتشاركها.
It's a world of peace and prosperity and sustainability.
إنه عالم السلام والإزدهار والإستدامة.
And when we heard a lot of the presentations
وعندما سمعنا نحن الكثير من التقديمات،
over the last couple of days,
خلال اليومين الماضيين،
Ed Wilson and the pictures of James Nachtwey,
آد ويلسون والصور التي قدمها جيمس ناشتوي،
I think we all realized how far we have to go
أعتقد أننا جميعاً أدركنا كم نحن بعيدون عن الوصول
to get to this new version of humanity
لنموذج جديد للإنسانية
that I like to call "Humanity 2.0."
التي أسميها " إنسانية 2.0"
And it's also something that resides in each of us,
وهو كذلك شئ موجود في كلٌ منّا،
to close what I think
لإغلاق ما أعتقد أنهما
are the two big calamities in the world today.
المصيبتين الكبيرتين في عالم اليوم.
One is the gap in opportunity --
أولاً هي الفارق في الفرص--
this gap that President Clinton last night
هذا الفارق الذي أسماه الرئيس كلينتون ليلة أمس
called uneven, unfair and unsustainable --
المتفاوت وغير عادل وغير مستدام--
and, out of that, comes poverty and illiteracy and disease
ومن ذلك يأتي الفقر والجهل والمرض
and all these evils that we see around us.
وهذه الشرور التي نراها حولنا.
But perhaps the other, bigger gap is what we call the hope gap.
لكن ربما الفارق الأكبر الآخر هي ما نسميه فارق الأمل.
And someone, at some point, came up with this very bad idea
وشخص ما في نقطة ما قد توصل لهذه الفكرة السيئة للغاية
that an ordinary individual couldn't make a difference in the world.
أن الفرد العادي لا يمكنه إحداث فارق في العالم.
And I think that's just a horrible thing.
وأنا أعتقد أن ذلك شئ مريع للغاية.
And so chapter one really begins today, with all of us,
ولذا فالفصل الأول يبدأ اليوم حقاً، بنا جميعاً،
because within each of us is the power to
لأن في كل منا القوة
equal those opportunity gaps and to close the hope gaps.
لمساواة فوارق الفرصة تلك ولتقريب فوارق الأمل.
And if the men and women of TED
وإن كان الرجال والنساء في تيد
can't make a difference in the world, I don't know who can.
لا يمكنهم إحداث فارق في العالم، فأنا لا أعلم من يستطيع.
And for me, a lot of this started when I was younger
وبالنسبة لي، بدأ الكثير من هذا عندما كنت أصغر في العمر
and my family used to go camping in upstate New York.
وأعتادت أسرتي على التخييم في ولاية نيويورك.
And there really wasn't much to do there for the summer,
ولم يكن هناك الكثير لفعله هناك لفصل الصيف،
except get beaten up by my sister or read books.
بإستثناء أن تضربني أختي أو قراءة الكتب.
And so I used to read authors like James Michener
ولذا فقد أعتدت على القراءة لمؤلفين مثل جيمس ميشنر
and James Clavell and Ayn Rand.
وجيمس كلافيل وآين راند.
And their stories made the world seem a very small
وقصصهم جعلت العالم يبدو كأنه صغيراً جداً
and interconnected place.
ومكان مترابط بشدة.
And it struck me that if I could write stories
وقد أدهشني أنه إن أستطعت كتابة القصص
that were about this world as being small and interconnected,
حول هذا العالم كشئ صغير ومترابط،
that maybe I could get people interested in the issues
وأنه ربما أستطعت الحصول على أناس مهتمين بالقضايا
that affected us all, and maybe engage them to make a difference.
التي تؤثر فينا جميعاً. وربما أشركهم في إحداث فرق.
I didn't think that was necessarily the best way to make a living,
لم أعتقد أنه من الضروري أن يكون أفضل طريق لجني المال،
so I decided to go on a path to become financially independent,
لذا فقد قررت أن أذهب في هذا المسار لأصبح مستقل مادياً،
so I could write these stories as quickly as I could.
بحيث يمكنني كتابة هذه القصص بأسرع ما يمكن.
I then had a bit of a wake-up call when I was 14.
ثم تلقيت شئ مثل جرس المنبه عندما بلغت 14 عاماً.
And my dad came home one day
وجاء والدي إلى البيت في يوم ما
and announced that he had cancer, and it looked pretty bad.
وأعلن أن لديه سرطان وقد بدى شيئاً سيئاً.
And what he said was, he wasn't so much afraid that he might die,
وما قاله كان، إنه ليس خائفاً بشدة كونه سيموت،
but that he hadn't done the things that he wanted to with his life.
لكن أنه لم يفعل الأشياء التي يريد فعلها بحياته.
And knock on wood, he's still alive today, many years later.
وأضربوا الخشب، ما يزال حياً اليوم، بعد سنوات عديدة.
But for a young man that made a real impression on me,
لكن بالنسبة لشاب يافع خلّف ذلك إنطباعاً حقيقياً عليّ:
that one never knows how much time one really has.
أن الشخص لا يعلم كم تبقى له من الوقت ليعيش.
So I set out in a hurry. I studied engineering.
لذا فقد قررت على عجالة. درست الهندسة.
I started a couple of businesses
وبدأت عدة أعمال
that I thought would be the ticket to financial freedom.
التي أعتقدت أنها ستكون تذكرتي للحرية المالية.
One of those businesses was a computer rental business
أحد تلك الأعمال كان شركة لإستئجار الحواسيب
called Micros on the Move,
تسمى ميكروس على الإنتقال،
which is very well named,
الذي كان أسماً مناسباً،
because people kept stealing the computers.
لأن الناس ظلوا يسرقون الحواسيب.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
So I figured I needed to learn a little bit more about business,
لذا فقد عرفت أنني بحاجة لتعلم القليل أكثر عن الأعمال،
so I went to Stanford Business School and studied there.
لذا فقد ذهبت لمدرسة ستان فورد للأعمال ودرست هناك.
And while I was there, I made friends with a fellow
وبينما كنت هناك إنشأت صداقة مع زميل
named Pierre Omidyar, who is here today. And Pierre, I apologize
يسمى بيري أوميديار، الذي هو هنا اليوم. ويا بيري، أنا أعتذر
for this. This is a photo from the old days.
لهذه -- هذه الصورة من الأيام الخوالي.
And just after I'd graduated, Pierre came to me
وبعد التخرج مباشرة، جائني بيري و --
with this idea to help people
مع هذه الفكرة لمساعدة الناس
buy and sell things online with each other.
بيع وشراء الأشياء على الإنترنت مع بعضنا البعض.
And with the wisdom of my Stanford degree,
ومع الحكمة وشهادتي من ستان فورد،
I said, "Pierre, what a stupid idea."
قلت، " بيري، ما هذه الفكرة الغبية."
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And needless to say, I was right.
ولا أحتاج للقول أنني كنت على حق.
But right after that, Pierre -- in '96, Pierre and I left our full-time jobs
لكن بعد ذلك مباشرة، بيري-- في عام 96، ترك بيري وأنا عملنا الدائم
to build eBay as a company. And the rest of that story, you know.
لإقامة eBay كشركة. وبقية القصة، أنتم تعلمونها.
The company went public two years later
هذا الشركة أصبحت عام بعد عامين
and is today one of the best known companies in the world.
واليوم هي أحد افضل الشركات المعروفة في العالم.
Hundreds of millions of people use it in hundreds of countries, and so on.
مئات الملايين من الناس يستخدمونها في مئات البلدان، وهلمجرا.
But for me, personally, it was a real change.
لكن بالنسبة لي شخصياً، لكن كان تغييراً حقيقياً.
I went from living in a house with five guys in Palo Alto
وانتقلت من العيش في بيت مع خمسة أشخاص في بالو ألتو
and living off their leftovers,
والعيش على بقايا طعامهم،
to all of a sudden having all kinds of resources.
إلى فجأة إمتلاك كل الموارد.
And I wanted to figure out how I could
وقد أردت معرفة كيف يمكنني
take the blessing of these resources and share it with the world.
أخذ بركة هذه الموارد وتقاسمها مع العالم.
And around that time, I met John Gardner,
وفي ذلك الوقت تقريباً إلتقيت مع جون غاردنر،
who is a remarkable man.
الذي هو رجل معروف.
He was the architect of the Great Society programs
لقد كان المهندس المعماري لبرامج مجتمع عظيم
under Lyndon Johnson in the 1960s.
في ليندون جونسون في الستينات.
And I asked him what he felt was the best thing I could do,
وسألته عن ما يشعر أنه أفضل شئ يمكنني فعله،
or anyone could do, to make a difference
أو أي شخص قد يفعله، لإحداث التغيير
in the long-term issues facing humanity.
في قضايا الأمد البعيد التي تواجه البشرية.
And John said, "Bet on good people doing good things.
وقال جون، " راهن على الناس الجيدين الذين يفعلون الأشياء الجيدة.
Bet on good people doing good things."
راهن على الناس الجيدين الذين يفعلون الأشياء الجيدة."
And that really resonated with me.
وقد ترك ذلك أثراً لديّ.
I started a foundation
لذا أسست مؤسسة
to bet on these good people doing good things.
للمراهنة على هؤلاء الناس الجيدين الذين يفعلون أشياء جيدة.
These leading, innovative, nonprofit folks,
هؤلاء الزملاء الرواد، المبتكرين الذين لا يرجون الربح،
who are using business skills in a very leveraged way
الذين يستخدمون مهارات الأعمال بطريقة فعّالة للغاية
to solve social problems.
لحلحلة مشاكل إجتماعية.
People today we call social entrepreneurs.
الناس الذين نسميهم اليوم بأصحاب المشاريع الاجتماعية.
And to put a face on it, people like Muhammad Yunus,
ولتسمية بعضهم، أناس مثل محمد يونس،
who started the Grameen Bank,
الذي أنشأ بنك غرامين،
has lifted 100 million people plus out of poverty around the world,
الذي رفع ما يزيد على 100 مليون شخص من الفقر حول العالم،
won the Nobel Peace Prize.
الفائز بجائزة نوبل.
But there's also a lot of people that you don't know.
لكن هناك أيضاً الكثير من الناس الذين لا تعرفونهم.
Folks like Ann Cotton, who started a group called CAMFED in Africa,
زملاء مثل آن كوتون، التي بدأت مجموعة تسمى كامفيد في أفريقيا
because she felt girls' education was lagging.
لأنها شعرت بأن تعليم البنات متخلف.
And she started it about 10 years ago,
وقد بدأت قبل 10 سنوات تقريباً
and today, she educates over a quarter million African girls.
واليوم، تقوم بتعليم زيادة على ربع مليون فتاة أفريقية.
And somebody like Dr. Victoria Hale,
وشخصية مثل د.فيكتوريا هيل،
who started the world's first nonprofit pharmaceutical company,
التي بدأت أول شركة عقاقير غير ربحية في العالم.
and whose first drug will be fighting visceral leishmaniasis,
والتي كان أول عقاقيرها لمكافحة داء الليشمانيات الحشوي ،
also known as black fever.
والمعروفة كذلك بالحمى السوداء.
And by 2010, she hopes to eliminate this disease,
وهي تأمل بحلول عام 2010 التخلص من هذا المرض،
which is really a scourge in the developing world.
الذي هو حقاً كارثة في الدول النامية.
And so this is one way to bet
وإذاً فهذا -- هذه أحدى الطرق التي أراهن
on good people doing good things.
بها على الناس الجيدين الذين يفعلون أشياء جيدة.
And a lot of this comes together in a philosophy of change
ويأتي الكثير من هذا مصحوباً بفلسفة التغيير
that I find really is powerful.
التي أجدها قوية حقاً.
It's what we call, "Invest, connect and celebrate."
وهي ما نسميه، " إستثمر، تواصل واحتفل."
And invest: if you see good people doing good things,
وإستثمر-- إذا رأيت أناس جيدين يفعلون أشياء جيدة،
invest in them. Invest in their organizations,
إستثمر فيهم. إستثمر في منظماتهم.
or in business. Invest in these folks.
أو في الأعمال، إستثمر في أولئك الزملاء.
Connecting them together through conferences --
قم بربطهم سوياً عبر مؤتمرات،
like a TED -- brings so many powerful connections,
مثل تيد، تجلب الكثير من التواصل القوي،
or through the World Forum on Social Entrepreneurship
أو عبر المنتدى العالمي لرجال الأعمال الإجتماعية
that my foundation does at Oxford every year.
الذي تعقده مؤسستي في أوكسفورد سنوياً.
And celebrate them: tell their stories,
وأحتفي بهم، سوّق قصصهم،
because not only are there good people doing good work,
ليس فقط لأنهم أناس جيدون يقومون بأشياء جيدة،
but their stories can help close these gaps of hope.
لكن قصصهم يمكنها أن تساعد في تقليل فوارق الأمل هذه.
And it was this last part of the mission, the celebrate part,
وقد كان الجزء الأخير من المهمة، جزء الإحتفال،
that really got me back to thinking when I was a kid
الذي أرجعني للتفكير حقاً عندما كنت طفلاً
and wanted to tell stories to get people involved
وأردت حكي القصص للحصول على الناس
in the issues that affect us all.
ليشاركوا في القضايا التي تؤثر بنا جميعاً.
And a light bulb went off,
ومن ثم خطرت لي فكرة
which was, first, that I didn't actually have to do the writing myself, I could find writers.
التي كانت في البداية، ولأنه لم يتوجب علي فعل الكتابة بنفسي، كان بإ ستطاعتي إيجاد كُتّاب.
And then the next light bulb was, better than just writing,
ومن ثم خطرت لي فكرة ثانية ، أفضل من الكتابة فقط،
what about film and TV, to get out to people in a big way?
كانت حول الأفلام والتلفاز، للحصول على الناس بطريقة أكبر؟
And I thought about the films that inspired me,
وقد فكرت حول الأفلام التي ألهمتني،
films like "Gandhi" and "Schindler's List."
أفلام مثل " غاندي" و " قائمة شيندلر"
And I wondered who was doing these kinds of films today.
وقد تعجبت حول من يقوم بمثل هذه الأفلام اليوم.
And there really wasn't a specific company
ولم تكن هناك شركة محددة
that was focused on the public interest.
تركز على القضايا العامة.
So, in 2003, I started to make my way around Los Angeles
لذا ففي عام 2003، بدأت في جولتي حول لوس أنجلوس
to talk about the idea of a pro-social media company
لأتحدث حول فكرة شركة إعلامية تخدم الشؤون الإجتماعية
and I was met with a lot of encouragement.
وقد لاقيت الكثير من التشجيع.
One of the lines of encouragement
أحد خطوط التشجيع
that I heard over and over was,
الذي سمعته مراراً وتكراراً كان،
"The streets of Hollywood are littered with the carcasses of people like you,
" شوارع هوليوود مليئة بالكثير من الجثث المتناثرة لأناس من أمثالك،
who think you're going to come to this town and make movies."
الذين يعتقدون أنك ستأتي لهذه المدينة وتصنع الأفلام".
And then of course, there was the other adage.
بعد ذلك بالطبع، كان هناك قول مأثور،
"The surest way to become a millionaire
" أضمن طريقة لتصبح مليونيرا
is to start by being a billionaire and go into the movie business."
هو أن تبدأ من كونك ملياردير وتدخل في صناعة الأفلام."
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Undeterred, in January of 2004, I started Participant Productions
دون أن أُبالي بهذا ، في يناير عام 2004 بدأت المشاركة في إنتاج الأفلام
with the vision to be a global media company
مع هدف لتكوين شركة إعلامية عالمية
focused on the public interest.
تركز على القضايا العامة.
And our mission is to produce entertainment
وكانت مهمتنا هي إنتاج الترفيه
that creates and inspires social change.
الذي يصنع ويلهم التغيير الإجتماعي.
And we don't just want people to see our movies
ونحن لا نريد الناس فقط أن يشاهدوا أفلامنا
and say, that was fun, and forget about it.
ويقولوا لقد كان ممتعاً، وينسونها.
We want them to actually get involved in the issues.
نحن نريدهم أن يشاركوا حقاً في هذه القضايا.
In 2005, we launched our first slate of films,
في عام 2005 بدأنا، أول قائمة أفلامنا،
"Murder Ball," "North Country," "Syriana"
"Murder Ball," "North Country," "Syriana"
and "Good Night and Good Luck."
و"Good Night and Good Luck."
And much to my surprise, they were noticed.
وما فاجأني جداً، لقد كانت ملحوظة.
We ended up with 11 Oscar nominations for these films.
أنتهى بنا الحال ب 11 ترشيح لجائزة الأوسكار لهذه الأفلام.
And it turned out to be a pretty good year for this guy.
وقد وضح أنها سنة جيدة لهذا الشخص.
Perhaps more importantly,
ربما أكثر أهمية،
tens of thousands of people joined the advocacy programs
عشرات الألوف من الناس شاركوا في برامج التأييد
and the activism programs
وبرامج الناشطين
that we created to go around the movies.
التي أنشأناها لتتحلق حول الأفلام.
And we had an online component of that,
وقد كان لدينا عنصراً على الإنترنت لذلك،
our community sect called Participate.net.
قطاع مجتمعنا يسمى Participate.net.
But with our social sector partners, like the ACLU and PBS and the
لكن مع قطاع شركائنا الإجتماعيين، مثل ACLU و PBS
Sierra Club and the NRDC, once people saw the film,
نادي سييرا و NRDC، بمجرد أن شاهد الناس الفيلم،
there was actually something they could do to make a difference.
كان لديهم شئ يمكنهم فعله، لإحداث فرق.
One of these films in particular, called "North Country," was actually
أحد هذه الأفلام تحديداً يسمى " North Country،" كان حقاً
kind of a box office disaster.
نوع من كارثة على شباك التذاكر.
But it was a film that starred Charlize Theron
لكنه كان فيلما بطولة تشارليز ثيرون
and it was about women's rights, women's empowerment,
وقد كان حول حقوق المرأة، وتعزيز المرأة،
domestic violence and so on.
العنف المنزلي وهلمجرا.
And we released the film at the same time that
وقد أطلقنا الفيلم في نفس الوقت الذي
the Congress was debating the renewal of the Violence Against Women Act.
كان الكونغرس يجادل في تجديد قانون العنف ضد المرأة.
And with screenings on the Hill, and discussions,
ومع العرض على هيل والمناقشات،
and with our social sector partners,
ومع شركاؤنا في القطاع الإجتماعي،
like the National Organization of Women,
مثل المنظمة الوطنية للمرأة،
the film was widely credited
أخذ الفيلم إستحساناً واسعاً
with influencing the successful renewal of the act.
مع تأثير التجديد الناجح للقانون.
And that to me, spoke volumes, because it's --
وكان ذلك بالنسبة لي، "أصوات وجدت صدى "، لأنه --
the film started about a true-life story
الفيلم بدأ حول قصة واقعية من الحياة.
about a woman who was harassed, sued her employer,
حول إمرأة تم التحرش بها، رفعت قضية على مخدمها،
led to a landmark case that led to the Equal Opportunity Act,
ما أدى لقضية شهيرة وقاد ذلك إلى قانون الفرص المتكافئة،
and the Violence Against Women Act and others.
وقانون العنف ضد المرأة وأشياء أخرى.
And then the movie about this person doing these things,
ثم أن الفيلم حول هذا الشخص الذي يفعل تلك الأشياء،
then led to this greater renewal.
بعد ذلك قاد لهذا التجديد الأعظم للقانون .
And so again,
ولذا مجدداً،
it goes back to betting on good people doing good things.
الأمر يرجع للمراهنة على أناس جيدون يفعلون أشياء جيدة.
Speaking of which, our fellow TEDster, Al --
بحديثنا عنهم، زميلنا في تيد ، آل "غور"،
I first saw Al do his slide show presentation
في البداية لقد شاهدت شرائح تقديم آل
on global warming in May of 2005.
حول الإحتباس الحراري في مايو عام 2005.
At that point, I thought I knew something about global warming.
في ذلك الوقت فكرت أنني أعرف شيئاً حول الإحتباس الحراري.
I thought it was a 30 to 50 year problem.
لقد فكرت أنها كانت مشكلة تستغرق 30 إلى 50 عاماً.
And after we saw his slide show,
وبعد أن رأيت شرائحه،
it became clear that it was much more urgent.
لقد أصبح واضحاً أنها أكثر إلحاحاً مما نتصور بكثير.
And so right afterwards, I met backstage with Al, and
ثم بعد ذلك مباشرة، إلتقيت خلف المسرح ب "آل" و
with Lawrence Bender, who was there, and Laurie David,
مع لورانس بيندر الذي كان هناك، ولواري ديفيد
and Davis Guggenheim,
وديفيد غوجينهيم،
who was running documentaries for Participant at the time.
الذي كان يعمل الأفلام الوثائقية للمؤسسة في ذلك الوقت.
And with Al's blessing, we decided on the spot to turn it into a film,
ومع مباركة "آل"، قررنا في الحال أن نحولها إلى فيلم،
because we felt that we could get the message out there
لأننا شعرنا أننا نستطيع أخذ الرسالة من هناك
far more quickly than having Al go around the world,
بصورة أسرع عن جولة "آل" حول العالم،
speaking to audiences of 100 or 200 at a time.
متحدثاً لحضور من 100 شخص إلى 200 كل مرة.
And you know, there's another adage in Hollywood,
وكما تعلمون، هناك قول آخر مأثور في هوليوود،
that nobody knows nothing about anything.
هو أنه لا شخص يعلم شئ عن أي شئ.
And I really thought this was going to be
وقد أعتقدت بالفعل أن هذا سيكون
a straight-to-PBS charitable initiative.
مباشرة نحو مبادرة PBS الخيرية.
And so it was a great shock to all of us
ولذا فقد كانت صدمة كبيرة لنا جميعاً
when the film really captured the public interest,
عندما حصل الفيلم على إهتمام الجمهور،
and today is mandatory viewing in schools in England and Scotland,
واليوم هو أساسي الحضور في المدارس في إنلجترا واستكوتلاندا،
and most of Scandinavia.
ومعظم دول اسكندافيا.
We've sent 50,000 DVDs to high school teachers in the U.S.
لقد أرسلنا 500،000 قرص DVD لمدرسي المدارس في الولايات المتحدة
and it's really changed the debate on global warming.
وقد غيّر بالفعل الجدل حول الإحتباس الحراري.
It was also a pretty good year for this guy.
لقد كانت سنة جيدة حقاً لهذا الشخص.
We now call Al the George Clooney of global warming.
نحن نطلق على "آل" الآن جورج كلوني للإحتباس الحراري.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And for Participant, this is just the start.
وبالنسبة للمشاركين، هذه مجرد البداية.
Everything we do looks at the major issues in the world.
كل شئ نفعله يبدو قضية رئيسية في العالم.
And we have 10 films in production right now,
ولدينا 10 أفلام في الإنتاج حالياً
and dozens others in development.
وحفنة من الأفلام الأخرى في التطوير.
I'll quickly talk about a few coming up.
سأتحدث بسرعة حول قلة من التي ستأتي قريباً.
One is "Charlie Wilson's War," with Tom Hanks and Julia Roberts.
واحد هو " حرب تشاري وليسون،" مع توم هانكس وجوليا روبرتس.
And it's the true story of Congressman Charlie Wilson, and
وهي قصة حقيقية لعضو مجلس الشيوخ تشاري ويلسون و
how he funded the Taliban to fight the Russians in Afghanistan.
كيف أنه قام بدعم طالبان، لقتال الروس في أفغانستان.
And we're also doing a movie called "The Kite Runner,"
وكنا كذلك ننفذ فيلماً يسمى "The Kite Runner,"
based on the book "The Kite Runner," also about Afghanistan.
بناء على كتاب "The Kite Runner," كذلك عن أفغانستان.
And we think once people see these films,
نعتقد أنه بمجرد رؤية الناس لهذه الأفلام
they'll have a much better understanding of that part of the world
سيحصلون على فكرة أفضل بكثير عن هذا الجزء من العالم
and the Middle East in general.
والشرق الأوسط عامة.
We premiered a film called "The Chicago 10" at Sundance this year.
قد تصدرنا فيلماً يسمى "The Chicago 10" في صندانس هذه السنة.
It's based on the protesters at the Democratic Convention in 1968,
وهو مبني على المتظاهرين في المؤتمر الديموقراطي عام 1968،
Abby Hoffman and crew,
آبي هوفمان والمجموعة.
and, again, a story about a small group of individuals
ومجدداً، قصة حول مجموعة صغيرة من الأشخاص
who did make change in the world.
الذين قاموا باحداث تغيير في العالم.
And a documentary that we're doing on Jimmy Carter
والفيلم الوثائقي الذي نقوم به حول جيمي كارتر
and his Mid-East peace efforts over the years.
وجهوده للسلام في الشرق الأوسط عبر السنين.
And in particular, we've been following him on his recent book tour,
وبالتحديد، كنا نتعقبه حول جولة كتابه الأخير
which, as many of you know, has been very non-controversial --
الذي يعرف العديد منكم، كان غير مثير للجدل بشدة --
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
-- which is really bad for getting people to come see a movie.
-- كان حقاً سيئ الحصول على الناس ليأتوا لمشاهدة الفيلم.
In closing, I'd like to say that everybody has the opportunity
في الختام، أرغب بالقول أن كل شخص لديه هذه الفرصة
to make change in their own way.
لإحداث تغيير بطريقته الخاصة.
And all the people in this room
وكل هؤلاء الناس في هذه القاعة
have done so through their business lives,
قد فعلوا ذلك عبر حياتهم العملية،
or their philanthropic work, or their other interests.
أو عبر أعمالهم الخيرية أو عبر إهتماتهم الأخرى.
And one thing that I've learned
وشيئ آخر قد تعلمته
is that there's never one right way to make change.
هو أنه ليس هناك طريق واحد صحيح لصنع التغيير.
One can do it as a tech person, or as a finance person,
يمكن أن يفعله شخص كتقني أو كمتخصص في المالية
or a nonprofit person, or as an entertainment person,
أو منظمات لا ربحية أو كعامل في قطاع الترفيه،
but every one of us is all of those things and more.
لكن كلٌ منا هو كل تلك الأشياء وأكثر.
And I believe if we do these things,
وأعتقد بأننا إن فعلنا هذه الأشياء
we can close the opportunity gaps, we can close the hope gaps.
يمكننا تقليل فوارق الفرص. يمكننا تقليل فوراق الأمل.
And I can imagine, if we do this,
ويمكنني تخيل أننا لو فعلنا هذا،
the headlines in 10 years might read something like these:
فأن عناوين الأخبار خلال 10 سنوات يمكن أن تكون مثل هذه:
"New AIDS Cases in Africa Fall to Zero,"
" حالات الإصابة الجديدة بالإيدز في أفريقيا تصل لصفر،"
"U.S. Imports its Last Barrel of Oil" --
" أمريكا تستورد آخر برميل للنفط" --
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
-- "Israelis and Palestinians Celebrate
-- " تحتفل إسرائيل وفلسطين
10 Years of Peaceful Coexistence."
بمرور 10 سنوات على التعايش السلمي."
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
And I like this one, "Snow Has Returned to Kilimanjaro."
ومثل هذا، " رجعت الثلوج لجبل كلمنجارو."
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And finally, an eBay listing for one well-traveled slide show,
وأخيراً، قائمة على موقع eBay لأحد الشرائح التي تنقلت جيداً،
now obsolete, museum piece. Please contact Al Gore.
عفى عليها الزمن قطعة تناسب المتحف -- رجاء أتصلوا ب "آل غور".
And I believe that, working together,
وأعتقد بأننا يمكن أن نعمل سوياً،
we can make all of these things happen.
يمكننا جعل كل هذا ممكن الحدوث.
And I want to thank you all for having me here today.
وأريد أن أشكركم جميعاً لدعوتي إلى هنا اليوم،
It's been a real honor. Thank you.
لقد كان شرفاً حقاً. شكراً لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Oh, thank you.
أوه، شكراً لكم.